<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Error Bar</title><link>http://errorbar.co.uk/</link><description>Error Bar - the evidence-based news blog</description><atom:link href="http://errorbar.co.uk/rss.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2016 19:15:17 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Democracy in the EU</title><link>http://errorbar.co.uk/posts/democracy-in-the-eu/</link><dc:creator>Drew Leonard</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Democracy in the EU&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Whose round is it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buying the drinks at the Error Bar this week is Boris Johnson, on behalf of the Leave campaign:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The independence of this country is being seriously compromised. It is this fundamental democratic problem – this erosion of democracy – that brings me into this fight." - &lt;a href="http://www.conservativehome.com/parliament/2016/05/boris-johnsons-speech-on-the-eu-referendum-full-text.html"&gt;Boris Johnson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several groups advocating Britain's exit from the EU have claimed that we need to "take back control", that the EU is fundamentally undemocratic and that we no longer get a say in our laws. They say that the system is broken and reform is impossible. But it's pretty easy to refute this by spending an hour on Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Error propagation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So on the face of it, arguing that we should vote to leave the EU is a bit silly, since authoritarian regimes tend not to give you that option. But setting that aside, let's look at some of the individual institutions that make up the EU and see how democratic each one is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;European Council:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Council sets the policy agenda and priorities for the EU, but has no role in making new laws. It consists of the heads of state or government of each member state, plus a President (who is elected by the European Council) and the President of the European Commision (proposed by the European Council and approved by the European Parliament). The UK's representative on the European Council is the Prime Minister. Since one of the criteria for a state to join the EU is &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/enlargement/policy/conditions-membership/index_en.htm"&gt;"stable institutions guaranteeing democracy"&lt;/a&gt;, in theory everyone on the European Council is elected by &lt;em&gt;somebody&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Council of the European Union:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Council of the EU - often just called "the Council", and not to be confused with the European Council - can discuss, amend and approve EU law. The exact members depend on the area being discussed, but the Council is always made up of the goverment ministers who deal with that policy area - one from each member state. So every member is a democratically elected representative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;European Commission:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This body proposes legislation and works with member states to implement EU law. Made up of one Commissioner from each member state, one of whom is the President. The President selects the other Commissioners (arguably not very democratic), but they then have to be agreed by both the Council (government ministers) and the Parliament (directly elected). So although the members &lt;em&gt;aren't&lt;/em&gt; directly elected, they have to go through several layers of approval by people who are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Court of Justice:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This body enforces EU laws and can invalidate them if a challenge is made. There's one judge for each member state on the Court, plus 11 Advocates General. These are all independent legal experts who are apponted by a panel in consultation with the governments of the member states. So just like the Council, the Court is not elected, but does have to be approved by elected governments. The Court is also a legal body rather than a representative one, so you can argue that it doesn't need to be as democratic anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;European Parliament:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an easy one. Members of the European Parliament are directly elected by the citizens of the EU member states. There are 751 seats on the Parliament, and the number of MEPs each member state gets depends on its population. The UK has 73, second only to Germany (96) and France (74). Any new legislation can only take effect if it's approved by Parliament, which can also amend that legislation. The Parliament also approves or rejects the Commision, so it has a lot of effective power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Unfair comparison time!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So every major part of the EU is either made up of elected representatives or is accountable to them. Compared to the system in the UK, this is incredibly democratic. Our laws have to go through the mostly unelected House of Lords, except on rare occasions and except for laws about taxes and other financial issues. All laws have to be approved by the Queen, even if the Lords are bypassed. Our head of government is not actually elected - the Queen appoints the person most likely to command confidence in the House of Commons, which by convention is the leader of the party with the most MPs. The Monarch also technically has the power to choose or dismiss ministers, summon or dissolve Parliament, and declare war, amongst other things. In practice, of course, these powers are almost never used, but the whole system mostly rests on the Queen not wanting to cause a fuss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Last orders&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of this information came from either the &lt;a href="http://europa.eu/about-eu/institutions-bodies/index_en.htm"&gt;EU's website&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Institutions_of_the_European_Union"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, so see those places for more detail. The &lt;a href="https://fullfact.org/europe/how-eu-works/"&gt;Full Fact&lt;/a&gt; website also has a lot of independently fact-checked info on the EU. And if you're still worried about the level of democracy in the EU, speak to your local MEP about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR:&lt;/strong&gt; To claim or suggest that the EU is wildly undemocratic is just drunken rambling - not worth paying any attention to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spotted an error? Evidence-based discussion welcome in the comments section.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://errorbar.co.uk/posts/democracy-in-the-eu/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2016 16:12:39 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>